Finding Aid for Department of Mechanical Engineering (University of Michigan) records, 1914-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Mechanical Engineering (University of Michigan) records
1914-2007
1922-1941
1993-2001
University of Michigan. Department of Mechanical Engineering.
0348 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Department of Mechanical Engineering dates from 1868, and it existed under various designations resulting from shifts and mergers in engineering, including at one time industrial engineering and applied mechanics. Records include minutes of faculty meetings, 1922-1941, and 1984-2007; advisory committee minutes, 1997-2007; and material on the 125th anniversary in 1993. Extensive visual materials document departmental activities and research including color and black and white photographs, contact sheets, slides, and negatives. The departmental website, as of June 2001, also forms a part of this record group.
21 linear feet
140.3 MB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was received in several small accessions beginning in 1995, one large accession in 2001, and two additional small accessions in 2007 and 2009 (Donor no. 8391 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
Department of Mechanical Engineering records are open with the exception of some personnel files closed in accord with university policy and state law.
The Department of Mechanical Engineering record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 4 and 19
The Department of Mechanical Engineering began in 1868 as the Mechanical Engineering program, with a mandate to instruct students in the new field of machine, power and marine engineering. Both the departments and its facilities grew steadily from 1900 to 1940. Although the department split and merged with other engineering departments over the years as new fields of engineering developed, one of the most significant shifts occurred in 1956 when the status of the Industrial Engineering section was elevated, and the department was renamed Industrial and Mechanical Engineering. Two years later Industrial Engineering split off from Mechanical Engineering altogether. Another major shift occurred in 1978 when the department merged with Applied Mechanics and became Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics (MEAM). However, in 2000 the departments split again, giving the department its present name. In 1984 the department left its home of eighty years on Central Campus (in the East and West Engineering Buildings) and moved to new, modern facilities, including laboratories, offices, and classrooms, on North Campus.
A detailed history of the department through 1993, including research projects and curricula, can be found in the publication 125 Years of Mechanical Engineering at The University of Michigan in the MEAM Publications record group (University of Michigan. Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics. Publications).
The Department of Mechanical Engineering record group is comprised of manuscript and visual materials transferred between 1995 and 2001. The materials are arranged in eight series Minutes, E-Mail to Faculty, Office Files, Contact Sheets, Photographs, Panoramic Prints and Slides, Negatives, and Website. The manuscript material covers the periods 1922 to 1941 and 1993 to 2007 while the visual materials are mainly from the time period 1985-2000. The earlier accessions include a series of faculty minutes covering the period from 1922 to 1941 and 1993 to 1999. The earlier accessions also include a small group of electronic mail correspondence (printout) that was sent from the central departmental office to the departmental faculty from 1993 to 1996. Subsequent accessions include a small selection of office files alphabetically arranged and additional faculty minutes.
Visual materials, documenting departmental activities ca. 1985-2000, form the bulk of the record group. The departmental website, as of June 2001, also forms a part of this record group. The visual materials in the record group include color and black and white photographs, contact sheets, slides, and negatives. The visual materials are either arranged by a numerical sequence or alphabetically by topic or last name. Materials in the numerical sequence filing system include 4 x 6 prints, contact sheets, and negatives. While the materials in the numerical sequence are categorized by format, the materials in this sequence were designed to form one system. That is the 4 x 6 prints, contact sheets, and negatives reference each other.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering & Applied Mechanics.; Mechanical engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Minutes, 1922-2007
  The Minutes series, 1922-2007 (5.0 linear feet), includes chronologically arranged minutes of both Faculty Meetings and Advisory Committees covering the periods 1922-1941 and 1984-2007. There is a considerable gap in this series between 1941 and 1984; this may be the result of individual chairs, rather than the department itself, overseeing records. Later minutes also frequently include meeting agendas, notes, handouts from meetings, and other information relating to decision-making at faculty and advisory committee meetings, such as faculty hiring and promotion and course approvals. The minutes of the Advisory Committee occasionally discuss personal matters and are subject to the 30-year personnel record restriction.
  - Faculty Meetings, 1922-1941; 1984-2007 (Box 1)
    - 1922-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1937-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 2004, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 2005, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 2006, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 2007, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Advisory Committee, 1984-2007
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985 (Box 4)
    - 1986 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2016 ]
    - 1987 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2017 ]
    - 1988 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2018 ]
    - 1989 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2019 ]
    - 1990 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2020 ]
    - 1991 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2021 ]
    - 1992 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2022 ]
    - 1993 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2023 ]
    - 1994 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
    - 1995 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
    - 1996 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
    - 1997 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2027 ]
    - 1998 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
    - 1999 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
    - 2000 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2030 ]
    - 2001 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2031 ]
    - 2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2032 ]
    - 2003, 3 folders (Box 19)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2033 ]
    - 2004, 3 folders (Box 19)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2034 ]
    - 2005, 3 folders (Box 19)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2035 ]
    - 2006, 2 folders (Box 19)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2036 ]
    - 2007, 2 folders (Box 19)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2037 ]
- E-Mail to Faculty (printouts), 1993-1996
  The E-Mail to Faculty series, 1993-1996 (.5 linear feet) includes printouts of e-mail messages and informational notices sent to the mechanical engineering faculty mailing list during this time period.
  - 1993-1994 (Box 19)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 19)
  - 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Anniversaries-125th (Box 20)
- Office Files, 1914-1993
  The Office Files series, ca. 1914-1993 (2.0 linear feet), is arranged in two subseries: General Files, and External Communications. The General Files subseries is an alphabetically arranged assortment of office files. Many of the files are background files for departmental annual reports and other departmental projects. A number of the files are from an earlier time period documenting the department's function of testing mufflers for various manufacturers during the early part of the 20th century. These files include black and white photographs of mufflers, drawings, graphs, and lab reports. The External Communications subseries is an arrangement of photographs, line drawings, graphs, and other background material used to illustrate faculty publications, press releases, and other departmental communications. The subseries is organized by the last name and first initial of the faculty member. The original arrangement of the subseries was maintained. The subseries includes one outsized folder of mechanical engineering drawings.
  - General Files
    - Annual Report (background files)
      - circa 1960-1973 (Box 20)
      - 1974-1976 (Box 20)
      - 1977 (Box 20)
      - 1978 (Box 20)
      - 1979 (Box 20)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 20)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 20)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 20)
      - 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - 1987 (Box 20)
    - Auto laboratory Parts and Engines, 1921 (Box 20)
    - Bolt, Jay 1908 Brush Model B, background materials, circa 1994 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, Deposition, and Reports, Yale Muffler Testing, 1941 (Box 20)
    - Departmental Histories, circa 1950-1994 (Box 20)
    - Lay, Walter general files and drawings, circa 1950 (Box 20)
    - Letterhead samples, undated (Box 20)
    - Marchant Calculator, circa 1941 (Box 20)
    - Mechanical Engineering Drawings
      - Debler, Walter, seventeen drawings, notes, and test questions, circa 1948 (Box 18)
      - Student Drawings for Mechanical Engineering 10, ten drawings, circa 1922 (Box 18)
    - PI Posters, undated (Box 20)
    - Report, Automotive Muffler Tests, (M.E. 33), 1914-1915 (Box 20)
    - Report, Frequency Analysis of Engine Exhaust Noise, (M.E. 255), Fall, 1955-1956 (Box 20)
    - Reports, Muffler Testing
      - #1961 muffler series, June 1926 (Box 20)
      - A.B. Stove Company, 1949 (Box 20)
      - Bingham Stamping and Tool Company, May 1930 (Box 20)
      - Geometric Stamping Company, 1927 (Box 20)
      - G.H. Morgenstern Union Metal Manufacturing Company, March 1931 (Box 20)
      - Globe Manufacturing and Stamping Company, circa 1929 (Box 20)
      - Kant Klog Muffler, November 1929; March 1931 (Box 20)
      - J.I. Quarmby and Sons, June 1926 (Box 20)
      - Potter Manufacturing Company, 1930 (Box 20)
      - Powell, 1930 (Box 20)
      - Urquhart Muffler, October 1930 (Box 20)
    - Reports, miscellaneous
      - The Application of TRS-DOS and Disk Basis to Statement Accounting, August 1981 (Box 21)
      - An Automotive Laboratory for the University of Michigan, January 1953 (Box 21)
      - A Study of the Effect of Value Timing and Lift on Engine Volumetric Efficiency, December 1930 (Box 21)
      - University Presidents from Mechanical Engineering and Mechanics, circa 1992 (Box 21)
    - Slides for College of Engineering Slide Show (paper printouts) (Box 21)
    - World Solar Challenge, (includes some e-mail correspondence), 1993 (Box 21)
  - External Communications
    - Akhavan, R., undated (Box 21)
    - Arpaci, V.S., undated (Box 21)
    - Aston-Miller, J.A., undated (Box 21)
    - Barber, J.R., undated (Box 21)
    - Borenstein, J., circa 1997 (Box 21)
    - Brei, D.E., undated (Box 21)
    - Ceccio, S.L., undated (Box 21)
    - Comninou, M.A., undated (Box 21)
    - Datsko, J., undated (Box 21)
    - Debler, W., undated (Box 21)
    - Dutta. D., undated (Box 21)
    - Ervin, R.D., undated (Box 21)
    - Felbeck, D., undated (Box 21)
    - Grosh, K., undated (Box 21)
    - Holmes, J.W., undated (Box 21)
    - Kannatey-Asibu, E., undated (Box 21)
    - Karnopp, B.H., undated (Box 21)
    - Kaviany, M., circa 1990s; 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Kikuchi, N., undated (Box 21)
    - Koren, Y., undated (Box 21)
    - Kota, S., undated (Box 21)
    - Keller, R., undated (Box 21)
    - Ludema, K.C., undated (Box 21)
    - Lin, L., undated (Box 21)
    - Mazumder, J., undated (Box 21)
    - Merte, H., circa 1987 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous Faculty Portraits, undated (Box 21)
    - Pan, J., undated (Box 21)
    - Perkins, N.C., undated (Box 21)
    - Pierre, C., undated (Box 21)
    - Schultz, A.B., undated (Box 21)
    - Schultz, W.W., ca, 1987 (Box 21)
    - Smith, G.E., circa 1999 (Box 21)
    - Sonntag, R.E., undated (Box 21)
    - Stein, J.L., undated (Box 21)
    - Papalambros, P.Y., circa 2000 (Box 21)
    - Tryggvason, G., circa 1991 (Box 21)
    - Ulsoy, A.G., circa 1992 (Box 21)
    - Ward, A.C., circa 1991 (Box 21)
    - Wineman, A.S., undated (Box 21)
    - Wu, S., (manufacturing lab booklet), undated (Box 21)
    - Wu, X., undated (Box 21)
    - Yang, W.J., undated (Box 21)
- Contact Sheets, circa 1985-2000
  The Contact Sheets series, ca. 1985-2000 (2.0 linear feet), is a numerical sequence of contact prints that coordinate with the 4x6 prints found in the Photographs series and the Negatives series. The contact sheets are held in large three-ring binders.
  - Cross Reference Index information (Box 5)
  - Log Index #0001-0399, circa 1985-1996 (Box 5)
  - Log Index #0400-0593, circa 1996-1998 (Box 5)
  - Log Index #0594-0735, circa 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Log Index #0736-0856, circa 1999 (Box 6)
  - Log Index #0857-0929, circa 2000 (Box 6)
- Photographs, circa 1985-2000
  The Photographs series, ca. 1985-2000 (10.0 linear feet), includes two subseries, 4x6 Prints and Topical. The 4x6 Prints subseries is a numerical sequence of 35 mm color photographs. The photographs date from the 1985-2000 time period. The 4x6 Prints correspond with materials in the Contact Sheets and Negatives series. The photographs in this series include views of award banquets, student projects, and faculty and staff. The Topical subseries is a series of photographs alphabetically arranged by topic. This subseries contains the most complete collection of faculty portraits. Most of the photographs in this subseries date from the 1990s, however, there are some earlier black and white photographs included. A number of these photographs seem to be reprints from the Michigan Historical Collections. The Topical subseries includes one outsized folder of large black and white photographs.
  - 4x6 Prints, circa 1985-2000
    - Packets #0010-0562 (Box 7)
    - Packets #0565-0745 (Box 8)
    - Packets #0746-0774 (Box 9)
    - Packets #0806-0880 (Box 10)
    - Packets #0881-0929 (Box 11)
  - Topical Images, circa 1924-2000
    - Annual Report images (Box 12)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 12)
        (one expandable folder)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 12)
    - Architecture, undated (Box 12)
    - ASME Student-Faculty Luncheon, April 2000 (Box 12)
    - Automotive Research, circa 1933-1990 (Box 12)
    - Automotive/Transportation, undated (Box 12)
    - Biomechanics, undated (Box 12)
    - Biomechanics Lab, July 1999 (Box 12)
    - Buildings and Aerial Views, undated (Box 12)
    - Campus Life, circa 1970-1990 (Box 12)
    - Classrooms, undated (Box 12)
    - Classrooms and Labs, circa 1924-1985 (Box 12)
    - Combustion, circa 1990s (Box 12)
    - Computational Mechanica, undated (Box 12)
    - Design, (includes some line drawings), circa 1990s (Box 12)
    - Distinguished Faculty, undated (Box 12)
    - Dynamics, undated (Box 12)
    - East Engineering Building, circa 1925-1985 (Box 12)
    - Engineering Research Center for Reconfigurable Machining Systems (ERC/RMS), undated (Box 12)
    - External Advisory Board, circa 1994-1995 (Box 12)
    - Faculty Portraits
      - circa 1950-1985 (Box 12)
      - circa 1990s, 2 folders (Box 12)
        (includes some negatives)
    - Faculty Portraits, undated, 2 folders; 1 Kodak box (Box 13)
    - Fluid Mechanics, undated; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Fluids Research, circa 1930-1965 (Box 13)
    - Formula SAE, Solar Car, undated (Box 13)
    - Heat Transfer, undated (Box 13)
    - High Tech Engine Test Car, undated (Box 13)
    - Inactive Faculty, circa 1980-1990 (Box 13)
    - Labs and Facilities, undated (Box 13)
    - Learning Center, circa 1990s (Box 13)
    - Lurie Tower, circa 1997 (Box 13)
    - Manufacturing, circa 1997 (Box 13)
    - Manufacturing Research, undated (Box 13)
    - MEAM Alumni, circa 1999 (Box 13)
    - MEAM Displays, undated; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - MEAM Events, miscellaneous, undated (Box 13)
    - MEAM Seminars, 1997-1998 (Box 13)
    - MEAM Staff, miscellaneous, undated (Box 13)
    - MEAM Team, circa 1990s (Box 13)
    - Mechanica (Box 14)
      - Fall 1997 (Box 14)
      - Fall 2000 (Box 14)
    - Mechanical Engineering 250, 350, 450, circa 1990s; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Mechanical Systems, undated (Box 14)
    - Memorabilia, circa 1991 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Graphics, undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Labs and Shops, circa 1959-1970 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Research (plus one outsized folder filed in Box 18), undated (Box 14)
    - NASA, circa 1989 (Box 14)
    - Photographs classified "Problem Photographs," (unidentified), undated (Box 14)
    - Pi Tau Sigma, Banquet
      - Fall 1996 (Box 14)
      - Fall 1997 (Box 14)
    - Robotics, undated (Box 14)
    - Solid Mechanics, undated (Box 14)
    - Student Cars and Projects, circa 1990s (Box 14)
    - Student Life
      - circa 1885-1962 (Box 14)
        (early image are reprints)
      - circa 1990s (Box 14)
    - Student Societies, circa 1990s (Box 14)
    - Sunrunner, 1990 (Box 14)
    - Symposium Photos, undated (Box 14)
    - Thermal Research (includes line drawings), undated (Box 14)
- Panoramic Prints and Slides, 1997-2000
  The series Panoramic Prints, and Slides, 1997-2000 (1.0 linear feet), includes a small number of panoramic photographs and a group of 35 mm slides. The color images are mostly winter and spring views of North Campus. The 35 mm slides are color slides and are stored in the original boxes they were received in. The slides are largely unidentified.
  - ERC/RMS Site Visit, May 1999 (Box 14)
  - Graduate Students, undated (Box 14)
  - North Campus Winter Snowstorm, December 1997 (Box 14)
  - Spring Colors, April 1999 (Box 14)
  - North Campus, undated (Box 14)
  - North Campus and Maria Comninou's class, March 2000 (Box 14)
  - 35 mm slides, undated; 24 containers; 1 binders (Box 15)
- Negatives, 1985-2000
  The Negatives series, 1985-2000 (1.0 linear feet), utilizes the same numerical sequence and organization found in the Contact Sheets series and the 4 x 6 Prints subseries.
  - Cross Reference Log (Box 16)
  - Photographic Negative Log, sleeve #01-0856-A, circa 1985-1999 (Box 16)
  - Negatives, circa 1985-2000
    - #010-028 (Box 16)
    - #0100-0051 (Box 16)
    - #0052-0102 (Box 16)
    - #0103-0139 (Box 16)
    - #0140-0199 (Box 16)
    - #0200-0250 (Box 16)
    - #0251-0291 (Box 16)
    - #0292-0366 (Box 16)
    - #0367-0485 (Box 16)
    - #0486-0546 (Box 16)
    - #0487-0597 (Box 16)
    - #0598-0649 (Box 16)
    - #0650-0720 (Box 16)
    - #0721-0774 (Box 16)
    - #0775-0820 (Box 16)
    - #0821-0880 (Box 16)
    - #0881-0905 (Box 16)
    - #0906-0929 (Box 16)
- Website, June 2001
  The Website series, June 2001 (1.0 linear foot and 1,899 digital records, 140.3 MB), comprises a point-in-time snapshot record of the departmental website. The snapshot of the website was captured by the department. The information found within this series is as of June 2001. The website content and structure is stored as both a paper printout and as a digital version on CD-ROM. The paper printout version is arranged in two large three-ring binders. The first binder includes the website sections, Academic Programs and Admissions, Program Requirements, News and Information, People, Research, and Student Organizations. The second binder includes departmental publications Annual Reports (1994-2000) Mechanic (1998-2000), and Graduate Program Handbooks (1996-1999). The CD-ROM version is a digital copy of the site as of June 2001. The CD-ROM version maintains the original functionality contained in the structure of the site through the use of hypertext links.
  - Volume One (paper printout and digital files stored on CD-ROM) (Box 17)
    - Academic Programs and Admissions
      - Program Requirements (Box 17)
    - News and Information (Box 17)
    - People (Box 17)
    - Research (Box 17)
    - Student Organizations (Box 17)
  - Volume Two (paper printout and digital files stored on CD-ROM)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1994-1995 (Box 17)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 17)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 17)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 17)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 17)
    - Mechanica
      - Volume 5, No. 1, Winter 1998 (Box 17)
      - Volume 5, No., Spring 1998 (Box 17)
      - Volume 5, No. 3, Fall 1998 (Box 17)
      - Volume 6, No. 1, Winter 1999 (Box 17)
      - Volume 6, No. 2, Spring 1999 (Box 17)
      - Volume 6, No. 3, Fall 1999 (Box 17)
      - Volume 7, No. 1, Spring 2000 (Box 17)
      - Volume 7, No. 2, Fall 2000 (Box 17)
    - Graduate Programs Handbooks
      - 1996-1997 (Box 17)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 17)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 17)